Guide to the Robert E. Apfel Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Robert E. Apfel papers
1973-2000
MS 1870
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.25
(2 boxes)
The collection comprises teaching and administrative materials documenting the career of Yale mechanical engineering professor Robert E. Apfel. Teaching materials include lecture notes, examinations, and exercises for courses in acoustics, dynamics, mechanical design, and practical applications of engineering research. Administrative files document the proposed restructuring of Yale's engineering programs in the late 1980s to the early 1990s.
Apfel, Robert E.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Nancy Apfel, 2006.
Conditions Governing Access
While the collection as a whole is open for research, box 2 is restricted until January 1, 2033 as established by Yale Corporation regulations.
Biographical / Historical
Robert E. Apfel was born on March 16, 1943, in New York City. He graduated magna cum laude from Tufts University in 1964 and received his PhD in Applied Physics, specializing in acoustics, from Harvard in 1970. He was a member of the Yale faculty for over three decades, serving as chair of the Council of Engineering during a critical time in the shaping of engineering education and research there. He was respected at Yale as a teacher and mentor of graduate students, receiving the Yale Graduate Mentor Award in 2002. He was an active member and served as president (1995-1996) of the Acoustical Society of America, receiving its Gold Medal Award in 2002. He published over 120 articles in thirty-six journals during his career. Apfel died in New Haven on August 1, 2002.
Scope and Contents
The collection comprises teaching and administrative materials documenting the career of Yale mechanical engineering professor Robert E. Apfel. Teaching materials include lecture notes, examinations, and exercises for courses in acoustics, dynamics, mechanical design, and practical applications of engineering research. Administrative files document the proposed restructuring of Yale's engineering programs in the late 1980s to the early 1990s.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically by type of material.
Apfel, Robert E.; Yale University -- Faculty
- Inventory, 1973-2000
  - Administrative files
    - Community outreach, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Proposed restructuring of Engineering programs, 1983-1993 (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Material in box 2 is restricted until January 1, 2033 das established by Yale Corporation regulations.
    - Reports relating to Yale Faculty of Arts and Sciences and Engineering programs, 1984-1997 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Material in box 2 is restricted until January 1, 2033 as established by Yale Corporation regulations.
    - Yale College foreign language requirement, 1981-1990 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Course materials
    - Acoustics, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Dynamics, 1973-1997 (Box 1, Folder 3-6)
    - Mechanical Design Studio, 1982-1999 (Box 1, Folder 7-10)
    - SynThesis, 1998-2000 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)